{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "This man criticized the use of wet nurses and advocated for breastfeeding by mothers in a 1752 thesis titled Nutrix Noverca. This man had to flee Hamburg after angering its mayor when he declared that a seven-headed hydra corpse he possessed was fake. Peter Forsskål, who died while on an expedition in Yemen, was among the seventeen dedicated “apostles” of this man. The author of Systema Naturae, for ten points, what Swedish naturalist is often called the “father of modern taxonomy\"?",
      "answer": [
        "Carl Linnaeus or Carolus Linnaeus",
        "Carolus a Linné"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "King Pyrrhus of Epirus used the excuse of enrolling his heirs in this program to justify an invasion of the Peloponesse. A trip to Crete inspired the semi-mythical figure Lycurgus [[lye-KUR-guss]] to introduce this system, including the use of a common mess hall and a restriction on bathing. This system, which was often led by more experienced men known as paidonomoi, was chronicled by the Athenian Xenophon, who put his own sons into this program while serving as a mercenary. The youth of Sparta were subjected to, for ten points, what twenty year program of militaristic training?",
      "answer": "Agoge ] or Agōgā"
    },
    {
      "question": "This act was meant to pressure another country into repealing its Orders in Council. This act was opposed by Secretary of the Treasury Albert Gallatin, who proposed Macon’s Bill Number One as an alternative. This act was passed in response to the Chesapeake- Leopard Affair and was represented in a comic depicting a snapping turtle biting the backside of a man who complains, “This cursed Ograbme.\" For ten points, name this act, promoted by Thomas Jefferson, that blocked foreign trade in response to British naval impressment.",
      "answer": "Embargo Act of 1807"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man deployed diplomat Afanasiy Pushkin to negotiate an \"Eternal Peace\" with the delegates of Charles IX [[the ninth]]. Dionysus the Grammarian attempted to unseat this man from power by convincing one ruler to divorce this counselor's sister, Irina. This man, Feodor Nikitich Romanov, and Vasili Shuiski served on the advisory council which effectively ran the nation for the son of Ivan the Terrible, Feodor I. The Time of Troubles began following the death of, for ten points, which non-Rurikid tsar?",
      "answer": [
        "Boris Godunov or Borís Fyodorovich Godunóv",
        "either underlined portion 2021-22 HS National History Bowl"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Elders from this group read scripture underneath multi-colored umbrellas on a holiday known as Sigd, or Mehlella. In one country, the \"Blood Bank Affair\" banned these people from giving blood out of fear of HIV. Operations Joshua and Solomon airlifted this group to one country, at the time led by Yitzhak Shamir. Members of this group who convert to Christianity to seek a better life are called Falash Mura. Referred to as \"exiles\" in Amharic, for ten points, what minority religious community has largely emigrated to Israel from Africa?",
      "answer": [
        "Ethiopian Jews",
        "Beta Israel",
        "Falash Mura",
        "Falashas before \"Falash\""
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "One theory claims the bones of this figure were stolen by several Yale alumni led by Prescott Bush while serving as Army volunteers at Ft. Sill. The distribution of mezcal was used by Mexican soldiers to massacre this chief's soldiers at Casas Grandes in Chihuahua. Multiple escape attempts by this figure were followed by his formal surrender to Nelson A. Miles in Arizona. A military leader of the Bedonkohe Apache was, for ten points, what man whose name is shouted by paratroopers when jumping out of planes?",
      "answer": "Geronimo or Goyaalé"
    },
    {
      "question": "Eric Nilles and Anil Menon conducted a 2020 study of thousands of employees at this company, revealing that COVID-19 infection rates were lower in those who already contracted the disease. The Technical University of Munich's engineering team won all four iterations of the Hyperloop competition hosted by this company. Amateur astronomer Bill Gray revealed that, in early 2022, the remnants of this company's Falcon 9 were slated to collide with the moon. The colonization of Mars is the end goal held by, for ten points, what extra-terrestrial exploration company founded by Elon Musk?",
      "answer": "SpaceX or Space Exploration Technologies Corporation"
    },
    {
      "question": "This researcher studied the cultures he labelled \"Totemic societies,\" including the Australian Aborigines and the Pueblo, in his work The Elementary Forms of the Religious Life. This man considered the trial of Socrates a \"necessary release of social tensions\" and \"a useful prelude to reforms\" in Athens in The Rules of the Sociological Method. The concept of anomie is used to illustrate reasons one may commit the title action in, for ten points, which French sociologist's work Suicide?",
      "answer": "Emile Durkheim or David Emile Durkheim 2021-22 HS National History Bowl"
    },
    {
      "question": "While serving in the Army Air Corps, this composer was commissioned to write his Cello Concerto for Raya Garbousova [[gahr-boh-SOH-vah]] by the Boston Symphony Orchestra. Olin Downes faced intense criticism after a New York Times review praising a string orchestra work by this composer, taken from a movement of his String Quartet in B minor. That piece by this composer was played during the announcements of the deaths of Franklin D. Roosevelt and John F. Kennedy. Arturo Toscanini premiered a piece by, for ten points, what American composer of Adagio for Strings?",
      "answer": "Samuel Barber or Samuel Osborne Barber II"
    },
    {
      "question": "The book The Man Who Never Was details an effort during this campaign that involved Ewen Montagu’s goading of one side to divert troops to another country. During this campaign, Operation Avalanche targeted the western part of its central region. Harold Alexander led an Army Group that oversaw this campaign which forced Adolf Hitler to abandon a planned Kursk Offensive and reinforce its central area. During this campaign, Generals Patton and Montgomery engaged in a race to see who could first reach Messina. For ten points, name this Allied campaign to capture an Italian island.",
      "answer": "Allied Invasion of Sicily"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This event began the day after a group of Greek immigrants celebrated Orthodox Easter. Cripple Creek veteran John Chase commanded one group of armed men during this event. Camp leader Louis Tikas was violently beaten during this event by Karl Linderfelt before being shot in the back and left near the train tracks for three days. Mother Jones organized the United Mine Workers strike against John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s Colorado Fuel and Iron Company that precipitated, for ten points, what 1914 massacre of coal miners?",
        "answer": "Ludlow Massacre"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "What detective agency, also responsible for the Battle of Blair Mountain, operated a machine gun-laden car called the \"death special\" during the Colorado Coalfield War?",
        "answer": "Baldwin-Felts Detective Agency"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man served as the chancellor of the Duchy of Lancaster as a member of the Labour Party. This man came into conflict with communist counter-protestors under Phil Piratin and Metropolitan Police officers led by Philip Game during a “battle” that led to the passage of the 1936 Public Order Act. That act outlawed the wearing of political uniforms in public demonstrations and responded to this non-Italian man’s \"Blackshirts.\" For ten points, name this leader of the British Union of Fascists who led a march that culminated in the Battle of Cable Street.",
        "answer": "Oswald Mosley or Sir Oswald Ernald Mosley, 6th Baronet"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In 1924, Mosley came within 100 votes of defeating this MP from Birmingham Ladywood, who went on to succeed Stanley Baldwin as prime minister.",
        "answer": "Neville Chamberlain or Arthur Neville Chamberlain"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This country's 1948 Civil War was sparked by the assassination of People's Vanguard leader Mora Valverde and the overthrow of Teodoro Picado. Quakers from Alabama who failed to become conscientious objectors moved to this country's town of Monteverde, which contains a cloud forest. This country's president, Jose Figueres Ferrer, abolished the army as a precaution against the militarism seen in other Central American countries. Formerly split between New Granada and New Spain, for ten points, what is this country between Nicaragua and Panama?",
        "answer": "Republic of Costa Rica or Republica de Costa Rica"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The League War of Costa Rica occurred while it was member state of the \"United Provinces of\" what geographic region?",
        "answer": [
          "Central America or Centroamerica",
          "United Provinces of Central America",
          "Provincias Unidas del Centro de América",
          "Federal Republic of Central America",
          "República Federal de Centroamérica 2021-22 HS National History Bowl"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Following the Battle of Alnwick, this ruler incorporated the counties of Westmoreland and Cumberland at the expense of the Scottish monarch, Malcolm III. Nobleman Walter Tirel was accused of killing this king with an arrow during a hunting trip, an assassination that may have been ordered by this king's sibling, Henry Beauclerc [[boh- KLEHRK]]. For ten points, name this Anglo-Norman king and son of William the Conqueror, nicknamed for his red hair.",
        "answer": "William II or William Rufus"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "William II and Henry I's mother shared what name with an \"empress\" who contested the English throne during The Anarchy?",
        "answer": [
          "Empress Matilda",
          "Empress Maude"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The book What the Eyes Don’t See chronicles this event, during which Doctor Mona Hanna-Attisha founded an organization to deal with its effects. An outbreak of Legionnaires’ Disease coincided with this event, which led to charges being sought against Rick Snyder. Leaching resulting from a lack of corrosion inhibitors partly caused this event, which occurred after a source of its central good was no longer treated at a sewage plant. For ten points, name this 2014-2019 public health crisis that affected a Michigan city.",
        "answer": [
          "Flint Water Crisis",
          "descriptive answers of the water crisis in Flint"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In 1936 and 1937, Flint witnessed what kind of protest which centered on a General Motors Plant? As part of these protests, workers occupy their workstations without performing any work.",
        "answer": "Sit-Down Strike"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The term “redlegs” referred to impoverished inhabitants of several islands in this body of water. The preacher Paul Bogle led a protest among inhabitants of an island in this body of water during the Morant Bay Rebellion. A Welshman who became lieutenant governor of an island in this body of water was Henry Morgan, who clashed with that island’s maroon population. Sugar plantations were built on islands in this body of water’s Lesser Antilles. For ten points, name this formerly pirate-infested sea containing Puerto Rico and Jamaica.",
        "answer": [
          "Caribbean Sea",
          "Mar Caribe",
          "or Mer des Caraïbes",
          "or Kiaribiyan Sii",
          "or Laman Karibe",
          "or Caraibische Zee"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "What Caribbean island contributed it's oil facilities to the Allied war effort following the Netherlands' capitulation in World War Two?",
        "answer": "Aruba 2021-22 HS National History Bowl"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "At an event in this city, Pete Seeger offered to use an ax to stop a performance because of the acoustics. In this city, Paul Gonsalves performed a saxophone solo for 27 choruses during a performance of Duke Ellington's \"Diminuendo and Crescendo in Blue.\" The playing of \"Maggie's Farm\" opened a performance in this city, in which a folk singer shocked a crowd by, for the first time in his career, playing an electric guitar on stage. For ten points, Bob Dylan \"went electric\" at a jazz festival in which Rhode Island city?",
        "answer": [
          "Newport",
          "Newport Folk Festival",
          "or Newport Jazz Festival"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Following a 1960 riot in Newport that canceled many jazz performances, Langston Hughes wrote an impromptu lyric called \"Goodbye, Newport Blues\" and brought it to which musician? This man founded Chicago blues with songs like \"Mannish Boy\" and \"Rollin' Stone.\"",
        "answer": [
          "Muddy Waters",
          "McKinley Morganfield"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "While serving as chancellor of New York, Nathan Sanford ran in this presidential election year, winning 30 vice-presidential votes. The “Wyoming Letters” promoted one candidate in this election year whom the Smithsonian claimed was not “reared on sweetmeats from the tables of kings and princes.” The Nashville Junto aimed to portray the losing candidate in this election year as the “Hero of New Orleans.” A defeat for a man given the moniker “Old Hickory”, for ten points, what was this year in which the election was decided by a “corrupt bargain” which favored John Quincy Adams?",
        "answer": "United States Presidential Election of 1824"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Which tertium-quid politician came in third in electoral votes during the election of 1824? This Georgia congressman served as Secretary of War and Secretary of the Treasury during the Madison administration.",
        "answer": "William Harris Crawford"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "American Home Front during World War One",
      "prompt": "Concerning the U.S. during World War One, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "\"Telegram\" named for a German minister which attempted to prompt a Mexican invasion of the U.S.",
          "answer": [
            "Zimmerman Telegram",
            "\"Note\" in place of \"Telegram\""
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "German food which temporarily had its name switched to \"Liberty Cabbage.\"",
          "answer": "Sauerkraut"
        },
        {
          "question": "Influential AFL president who led the Council of National Defense.",
          "answer": "Samuel Gompers"
        },
        {
          "question": "Term for gardens grown by Americans to supplement rations.",
          "answer": [
            "Victory Gardens",
            "\"Food Gardens for Defense\"",
            "both underlined portions required for alternate answers"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Congresswoman from Montana and pacifist who voted against U.S. entry into World War One and Two.",
          "answer": "Jeannette Rankin or Jeannette Pickering Rankin"
        },
        {
          "question": "George M. Cohan song which claimed \"The Yanks are Coming.\"",
          "answer": "\"Over There\""
        },
        {
          "question": "State in which an Imperial German agent set fire to a munitions factory in Lyndhurst.",
          "answer": "New Jersey"
        },
        {
          "question": "Social scientist who led Women in Industry Service, a sub-agency of the Department of Labor.",
          "answer": "Mary van Kleeck or Mary Abby van Kleeck 2021-22 HS National History Bowl"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Years of Lead [[\"led\"]]",
      "prompt": "Concerning the Years of Lead, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Southern European nation where the \"Anni di piombo\" occurred.",
          "answer": [
            "Republic of Italy",
            "Italia",
            "or Italian Republic",
            "or Repubblica Italiana"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Capital city where the Victor Emmanuel II Monument was bombed.",
          "answer": "Rome or Roma"
        },
        {
          "question": "Far-left guerilla \"Brigade\" named for a color associated with communism and which kidnapped a sitting prime minister.",
          "answer": [
            "Red Brigade",
            "Brigate Rosse"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Lombard capital city whose Piazza Fontana was bombed by terrorists in 1969.",
          "answer": "Milan or Milano"
        },
        {
          "question": "Socialist French president who gave leftist fugitives asylum.",
          "answer": "Francois Mitterand or François Marie Adrien Maurice Mitterrand"
        },
        {
          "question": "Christian Democrat and prime minister who was assassinated following his 1978 kidnapping.",
          "answer": "Aldo Moro or Aldo Romeo Luigi Moro"
        },
        {
          "question": "Playwright who fictionalized a terrorist incident in Accidental Death of an Anarchist.",
          "answer": "Dario Fo or Dario Luigi Angelo Fo"
        },
        {
          "question": "Former fascist commander who led an aborted ultranationalist coup during the Feast of the Immaculate Conception.",
          "answer": "Junio Valerio Borghese or Junio Valerio Scipione Ghezzo Marcantonio Maria Borghese"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Ashanti Empire",
      "prompt": "Concerning the West African Ashanti Empire, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Trade in which they participated, selling war captives for European goods.",
          "answer": "Slave Trade or Slavery"
        },
        {
          "question": "Small rodent covered in quills that appeared on the emblem of the King of the Ashanti.",
          "answer": "Porcupine"
        },
        {
          "question": "Modern Western African state where it was located, gaining independence under Kwame [[KWAH-may]] Nkrumah.",
          "answer": "Republic of Ghana"
        },
        {
          "question": "City that served as their capital.",
          "answer": "Kumasi"
        },
        {
          "question": "Ultimate symbol of power for their kings, a divine throne made of a precious metal.",
          "answer": [
            "Golden Stool or Sika Dwa Kofi",
            "full translation: Golden Stool born on a Friday"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "\"Cloth\" used by royals, now popular in the West and associated with Kwanzaa.",
          "answer": [
            "Kente Cloth",
            "Kete Cloth"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Majority ethnic group of the empire.",
          "answer": "Akan People"
        },
        {
          "question": "British commander who crushed the Ashanti and defeated the Madhist revolt in Sudan.",
          "answer": [
            "Garnet Wolseley or Garnet Joseph Wolseley",
            "or 1st Viscount Wolseley 2021-22 HS National History Bowl"
          ]
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The leader Treniota led a group from this country called the Samogitians against the Livonian Order at the Battle of Durbe. Duke Daumantas assassinated the first Grand Duke of this country, who possibly renounced Christianity and approved the construction of the Klaipeda Castle. Mindaugas (20 pts)",
        "led this country, as did a national hero who ended a civil war by making peace with Jogaila. This country, led by Vytautas [[vee-\"TAO\"-tahs]], was later linked to (10 pts)",
        "Poland in a namesake Commonwealth. For ten points, name this country in which Stephen Bathory established Vilnius University."
      ],
      "answer": "Republic of Lithuania"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Paracelsus [[pah-rah-SEL-sus]] believed this phenomenon occurred due to \"overheated blood,\" while local burghers attempted to end this craze by clearing the open-air grain market for two weeks. One theory concerning this phenomenon claims German peasants (20 pts)",
        "were exposed to the psychoactive ergot [[ER-got]] fungi occasionally found in rye bread. People afflicted with this phenomenon were brought to the grotto of St. Vitus. (10 pts)",
        "16th century Strasbourg was struck with, for ten points, what \"Plague\" during which people gyrated uncontrollably?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Dancing Plague or Dancing Mania",
        "St. Vitus's Dance"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A co-founder of this organization, along with his brother, Francis, oversaw Galaxy Magazine which employed Mark Twain. That man was William Conant Church, who co-founded this organization with an author of a popular manual (20 pts)",
        "its members often read. George Wingate was an early leader of this organization, the national profile of which was raised when Ambrose Burnside became president. (10 pts)",
        "For ten points, name this organization that promoted breech-loading varieties of its namesake weapon and was once led by actor Charlton Heston."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "National Rifle Association",
        "NRA"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) American missionary Daniel Vrooman created a 19th century map of this city which included an accurate depiction of its mercantile ghetto, the Thirteen Factories. Members of a nationalist student organization led by Huang (20 pts)",
        "Xing [[ZHING]] were massacred during this city's Yellow Flower Mound Uprising, a part of the larger Xinhai [[ZHIHN-HYE]] Revolution. This city names a \"System\" instituted by Qing [[CHING]] China which forced all western trade to be concentrated along the Pearl River. (10 pts)",
        "Canton is an alternative name for, for ten points, what capital of Guangdong?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Guangzhou",
        "Canton before mentioned 2021-22 HS National History Bowl"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This event is described as \"dark as the world of man, black as our loss / Blind as the nineteen hundred and forty nails / Upon the cross\" in Edith Sitwell's poem \"Still Falls the Rain.\" After Maurice Bendrix's home is destroyed in this event, Sarah Miles (20 pts)",
        "breaks off her affair in Graham Greene's novel The End of the Affair. A poem about this historical event ends, \"After the first death, there is no other\" and features a speaker who will not mourn the \"death, by fire, (10 pts)",
        "of a child.\" For ten points, name this often memorialized German bombing campaign against Britain during World War Two."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "The Blitz",
        "the Battle of Britain before mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man was criticized for taking an elephant-hunting trip to Botswana paid for by Mohamed Eyad Kayali. This man's mistress, Corinna zu Sayn-Wittgenstein-Sayn admitted to the press that this man had received millions of dollars in kickbacks from interests building the Haramain (20 pts)",
        "high-speed railway. In 2014, this leader was succeeded by his son (10 pts)",
        "Felipe after abdicating the throne. Living in self-exile since 2020 due to corrupt business dealings in Saudi Arabia, for ten points, who is this former king of Spain?"
      ],
      "answer": "Juan Carlos I"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) William F. Packer defeated this man in one election, preventing him from becoming the first Republican governor of Pennsylvania. This politician stated that \"Slavery has within itself the seeds of its own destruction\" in a speech given before running for Speaker (20 pts)",
        "of the House in 1849 as a Free Soil candidate. Jacob Brinkerhoff and Gideon Welles assisted in drafting a bill named for this man that arose from fears that Polk was promoting (10 pts)",
        "Southern interests through war. For ten points, give this namesake of an unpassed bill that would have banned slavery in territory gained during the Mexican-American War."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "David Wilmot",
        "Wilmot Proviso"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This writer was inspired by a 1934 coal miner uprising led by Belarmino Tomás to pen the play Révolte dans les Asturies. Jean-Paul Sartre and this writer contributed to the paper \"Combat,\" which (20 pts)",
        "served as counter-propaganda to Nazi disinformation in occupied France. The Daniel Defoe account Journal of a Plague Year inspired the tale of Dr. Bernard Rieux [[ROO]], who tries to cure the title pestilence in this author's The Plague. Ethnic tensions in his homeland of (10 pts)",
        "Algeria inspired, for ten points, which author's The Stranger?"
      ],
      "answer": "Albert Camus ] 2021-22 HS National History Bowl"
    }
  ]
}